Hi and welcome back.
In this video we're looking at lambda functions.
Here's a function and this function has two parameters.
As per usual Python standards, we've got a parameter
called x and then a comma that separates it
from the next parameter called y.
Now, as you know, whenever we call this function
we'll give it two parameters
and again they'll be separated by a comma
5 will go into x, 10 will go into y
and then this will return 15.
Now that we've covered functions in some of the forms,
we can look at a new form of function
and that's an anonymous function,
a function with no name.
But, wait, didn't it say in the last video
that functions are names for blocks of code?
And I did say that.
Add to here is a name for the block of code
that is enclosed within it
but there are also functions that don't have names.
They're anonymous functions
and they're useful in a small but important number of places
so in this section I just want to tell you
about anonymous functions, how to create them
and how to use them and soon, in a future section,
we're going to look into places
where they can be really useful
and, believe me, anonymous functions are -
pretty much everyone in programing -
they are really popular
particularly in some programing languages
so knowing about them is really useful
and when we reach that later section,
you'll be glad that you know more about anonymous functions.
So, by the way, anonymous function and lambda function
same thing in Python but in other programing languages,
they're just called anonymous functions.
So we've got this function here.
I have two things in two parameters
and returns the sum of them.
We can re-write this as a lambda function like so.
Pretty straight-forward I hope.
Sorry for that, I just hit the microphone there.
We've got the lambda - keyword.
That's a keyword in Python
and then we've got x comma y.
These are the two arguments.
Then we've got a colon which declares that what follows
is now something else and this here is
the return value of the function.
Notice how we don't have to type out return explicitly.
Lambda functions already know how to do that.
So how do you call these functions?
How do you run them?
We know that add two is 10 and 5, for example.
What about the lambda function?
Well it's a good question.
In Python, when Python realises that
something you've declared, like a function or a variable
or something like that is no longer going to be used,
Python automatically destroys it
in order to give you more performance
and free up memory in your computer and things like that.
This anonymous function doesn't have a name.
Ergo, therefore we cannot use it after
because we have no way of referring to it.
As soon as it's created, Python destroys it
and it says here, statement seems to have no effect.
We're defining, well, we're not really defining anything.
We're saying, hey this is a function
and then immediately destroyed, completely useless.
So if we wanted to use the lambda function,
we will have to put it inside brackets
and then, as usual, we put the brackets
just like for the add two function.
That means we're calling this thing that precedes it
with the values 10 and 5.
So there's lambda function here.
10 will go into x.
5 will go into y.
Notice how this is a staple in Python
and I was going to say cuisine
but that's really cuisine, is it?
This is a staple in Python programing.
Brackets mean call the function
and that works for good old normal functions
and lambda functions, too, same thing.
So you can, of course, print this out
which is starting to get quite confusing
but you can see that you get 15 also.
I'm not lying to you.
Now this is pretty terrible
because there's a lot a brackets in there.
It just doesn't make a lot of sense.
I mean, every time you want to use this lambda function,
you have to define it.
I mean, what's that going to do to performance.
It's not going to be good for performance,
let me tell you that.
Not only is it unreadable because it's confusing,
the fact that you have to define the function
every time you want to use it
is not particularly efficient either.
So what we can do is instead we can give it a name.
Let's say that we can say sum or add is
lambda x, y x plus y.
Now this anonymous function, we have given it a name.
It sort of defeats the purpose of
anonymous functions, didn't it?
Yes, it sort of defeats the purpose of anonymous functions
but there is a benefit to this
which is that this function is a really simple function
and it reads as, once you're accustomed to reading this,
it reads as this is a process that takes in these values
and it processes them to give you that.
Slightly simpler than defining the whole function,
less boilerplate, you know.
Readability is an important thing here
and for simpler functions, this can be more readable.
Okay, something important for me to say is
that as we've seen that these brackets are used
for calling functions,
either anonymous functions or proper functions,
lambda functions and "proper functions" are the same thing.
Inside Python, they're undistinguishable.
Whenever you can use one, you can use the other
and vice versa, of course.
Now let's talk about first-class functions.
First-class function means that
a function can be an argument to another function.
What does that mean?
Okay, let's define equal functions.
Let's define this function.
This is a pretty bizarre function
because it's called who, takes in a parameter called data
and another called identify
but this identify you can see is a function
because we're using the bracket notation after it
which means we're running a function
so we've got this identify function
and we're giving it the data function
in order to do something.
So, for example, we could define my identifier function
which given some data is going to return data name.
So if we do my identifier function
and we give it a dictionary name Jose
that is going to return data name.
I'm sorry, some data name.
The dictionary is going to be some data.
This function is going to return some data
and using square bracket notation is
going to access the name property of some data
which is going to be Jose
so if we print that, we get Jose.
Now that it's clear what my identifier function does,
let's extract the data into proper dictionary name
Jose surname Salvatierra.
There we go.
And instead of printing that,
we're going to print who of user and my identifier function.
Notice how my identifier function doesn't have
open and closing brackets at the end
because we're not executing this function,
we're just referring to it.
Now the who function does have the brackets
and inside the brackets,
we've got user, that's our dictionary,
my identifier function,
that's the function we defined up here
so this who function is going to run
and it's going to return running the identify function
which is my identifier function with data which is user.
So it's going to run my identifier function with user
and it's going to return the name Jose.
Let's run that.
As you can see, we get Jose out
and this is a very common way
of using first-class functions in Python.
You have a function that does something
but it is someway extended by the functionality
of another function that you pass in as an argument
that way you can decide what the who function is
going to retrieve from the data.
For this to make sense, assume you don't have access
to modifying the who function
because it's part of Python
or because it was written by somebody else.
You know, this is part of a library
that does have a few complex things
and you can pass in a function
to make the who function do something different
than it would otherwise do
and, of course, we could re-write this
slightly more concisely by using a lambda function
getting rid of my identify function
and instead passing a lambda x x name there.
This lambda function does the same
as our previous function did
and, once again, if we run this, we'll get Jose out.
So instead of defining a function
that needs a name and so on,
we can just create one right where it's used
here in the lambda function that does
exactly the same thing with less verbosity.
It's less boilerplate code.
Lambda functions are really useful
when you're using them as a first-class function
like we do here.
Okay, so this may not be terribly clear
and I appreciate that.
As we create our own projects knowing that this can be done,
will open some doors and I know it's not easy to see now,
but it took me a few years, actually, to realise
that this can be done.
I wasn't aware that this is something
that you could do in Python
and it would've made some things much simpler
so I just wanted to tell you about it now
before you're left wondering
whether there are better ways of doing things.
So now that we've introduced first-class functions
which are just functions that you pass as an argument,
we can introduce higher order functions.
A higher order function is the who function.
It's a function that accepts a function as an argument.
This is just some lingo for programing first-class functions
in Python because you can pass them as arguments.
Higher order functions are those
who accept functions as arguments.
Some programming languages don't support first-class
and higher order functions
but as we'll see throughout the course,
they can end up being quite handy,
particularly in cases like this one here.
You'll see many more examples as we move through
so don't worry.
This is not a utterly bizarre and useless functionality.
So with that said, let's move over to the next video.
So I'll see you there.