Hi, and welcome back.
In this video we are going to be looking at starting to move
our milestone project from JSON to our database.
If you skipped the last couple of videos
and you went straight from CSV to database, that's fine.
We are just going to make a couple of changes here.
Now the first thing to do is to...
in the create book table, we are going to create our table.
Now, we'll start by opening up a connection to the database.
For that, we're going to need SQLite3.
We're going to import SQLite3 instead of JSON.
That's going to give us a few errors in our file,
but that's okay for now.
To open a connection, you know how to do that,
we looked at that in the slides last couple of videos.
So, go ahead and pause the video and give it a go,
open up the connection, create your cursor,
and then come back for we will implement the query here.
I hope you got that.
What to do is of course connect first of all.
"Sqlite3.connect," and in here we're going to give it
that file that we want to store all our data in.
That's going to be data.db.
Notice that data.db is going to appear in our
projects directory, and not beside database.py.
So it'll appear at the top level, which is pretty nice.
Then we'll create a cursor.
Then we can perform the query
which is going to create our database.
We'll do that in a moment.
Then we'll have to of course, commit our connection
to make sure that the database does get created,
and the table is all in the file;
and at the end we will close the connection.
So by the way, I said "create database"
a couple of times there, I mean "create table."
We are going to be creating a table.
Now the SQL query is going to be a string
that we're going to put inside this execute method here.
It's really straightforward, all that we have to do
is say "create table." So pretty english-like so far.
Then, we'll give it the table name,
whatever we want to create, in this case
it's going to be called "books."
The table name here is for us
to understand what it's storing,
and also will be used when we want to retrieve data.
So "books" seems like a good name, so that we can then
know that we're storing books in it.
Then we'll also need what columns are in our table,
what types of data we want to store;
and these are going to be fairly simple.
We want to store the name of the book,
the author of the book, and the "read" status.
Okay, so that goes in brackets after the table name.
We also have to specify what type of data
is going into each of these columns.
"Name" is going to be a text,
"author" is going to be a text, and "read" is going to be
1 or 0, so it's going to be an integer.
SQLite only supports 5 types of data, so it's really simple.
"Null," which just means empty, or void, or no data in here,
very similar to Python's "none,"
"integer," which means a whole number,
"real," which means a floating point number,
"text," which just means any string,
and "blob," which is a binary data field
where you can store things like
images, or documents, PDFs and so forth.
So those are the 5 data types that SQLite supports.
And now, we've created here our table, "books"
with 3 columns: "name," "author," and "read."
Notice how we don't have an ID column here
because this is the only table we've got;
we don't need to relate this table
to any other table in our system, ergo we don't need an ID.
The name is going to be what's going to identify our table.
As we progress we are going to add some more
complexity to this, but whichever column
is going to be the main identifying column of your table,
you can signal it as a "primary key."
So that's "name text primary key."
And that just tells SQLite that "name"
cannot contain any duplicates, so that no 2 books
can have the same name;
and also it improves performance
when we are going to be searching for specific names.
The complexities of primary keys and what that entails
won't be explained in this course, but in other courses.
Here, I just want to talk about Python.
Now, when we run this, we will be creating
our data.db file and inside it will create our table.
And indeed, we can go ahead and run app.
And this, before we print this out we know inside our app
that we are calling "create book table."
So we can stop the app,
and now notice how data.db has been created.
We can open it, and this is some weird-ass data;
which represents whatever it is that SQLite is storing here.
Notice how it's not terribly readable,
but if you open data.db with your SQLite browser,
some more stuff will pop up.
Okay, this is how to create a table using SQLite.
You say "create table," then the table name,
and then the columns, one by one, separated by commas,
including the type of data, and for one column,
whether they are the primary key or not.
Okay, that's it for this video,
I'll see you on the next one
where we're going to be inserting data.